Educational Technology Services Records UA245
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Great Courses, 2014 -- 2017; UA245.001; 626 Digital Object(s); 1 Web sites
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 1., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.322
    Synopsis: A Theory of Motion Under Centripetal Forces -- The Theory as an Evidential Instrument -- The Theory Versus Physical Hypotheses -- The Evidence for the Physical Hypotheses -- The New Title, Versus the Old. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 1.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 2., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.323
    Synopsis: The New Title, Versus the Old -- The New "Laws" and Definitions -- The New Lemmas: Deriving Former Hypotheses. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 2.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 3., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.324
    Synopsis: The New Lemmas: Deriving Former Hypotheses. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 3.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 4., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.325
    Synopsis: The "A Priori Proof" of Copernicanism -- The Imperfectibility of Astronomy -- Implications for Orbital Astronomy -- Resistance and Planetary Motion. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 4.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 5., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.326
    Synopsis: The "A Priori Proof" of Copernicanism -- The Imperfectibility of Astronomy. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 5.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 6., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.327
    Synopsis: Resistance and Planetary Motion -- Projectile Motion on the Earth -- The Initial Exchange with Flamsteed. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 6.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 7., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.328
    Synopsis: The Initial Exchange with Flamsteed. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 7.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 8., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.329
    Synopsis: The Initial Exchange with Flamsteed -- Drafts of New Definitions: Absolutes. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 8.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 9., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.330
    Synopsis: Drafts of New Definitions: Absolutes -- Drafts of New "Laws": The Third Law. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 9.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 10., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.331
    Synopsis: Drafts of New "Laws": The Third Law -- Further Drafts of Definitions: The Concept of Mass -- The Law of Gravity Emerges. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 10.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 11 - Part 12., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.332
    Synopsis: The Law of Gravity Emerges -- Toward Universal Gravity: Weight Inertial Mass -- The Law of Gravity: Interaction vs.Force -- The Conception of Evidence in De Motu Version 1. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 11 - 12.
  - Notes to Philosophy 167: Class 14 -- Newton's De Motu Corporum, Version 3 -- Part 13., 2014-12-09; gc.phil167.333
    Synopsis: The Conception of Evidence in De Motu Version 1 -- The Conception of Evidence in Version 3 -- Intimations of a New Conception of Evidence -- An Evolution in Conceptions of Evidence -- Parallel Evolution in the Science of Orbital Motion -- Three 17th Century Revolutions in Evidence. Generally corresponds to the video segment: Class 14, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 1 - Introduction: The Discovery of High-Quality Evidence., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.1
    Synopsis: This video sets the expectations of the course, reviews the syllabus, and briefly discusses history and philosophy of science. Opening line: "This is a course totally focused on answering the question: How did we first come to have high quality evidence in any of the sciences?" Duration: 16:50 minutes. Section: Class 1, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 2 - Basic Astronomy: The Celestial Sphere., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.2
    Synopsis: This video provides a brief introduction to astronomy. Opening line: "So let's start looking at this. How did we first come to have high quality evidence in any of the sciences? Interestingly enough, it comes almost entirely from the evidence in question, comes almost entirely from the skies." Duration: 8:50 minutes. Section: Class 1, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 3 - Inequalities: The Sun and the Moon., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.3
    Synopsis: This video reviews the concept of inequality, the Sidereal day, the line of nodes and First Inequality of the Planets. Opening line: "All right. Now, we start getting the complications. The technical term is inequality. What inequality means is non-uniformity in motion." Duration: 6:51 minutes. Section: Class 1, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 4 - Inequalities: The Planets., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.4
    Synopsis: This video introduces the concept of Retrograde Motion. Opening line: "But now on top on that, the planets do something that the sun and moon do not do at all." Duration: 6:39 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 5 - Accounts of the Planetary Inequalities: the Babylonians, and Eudoxus., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.5
    Synopsis: This video introduces the concept of tropical period and synoptic period. Opening line: "The first sensible set of predictions on this is by the Babylonians. They discovered that if you looked for a long enough period you would see the patterns I just showed you start repeating." Duration: 8:48 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 6 - Accounts of the Planetary Inequalities: Aristotle's Principles of Celestial Motion., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.6
    Synopsis: This video reviews Aristotle's concept of the celestial run and introduces us to Ptolemy and Apollonius and other important thinkers. Opening line: "Aristotle has a separate work called On the Heavens, De Caelo, in which he doesn't so much talk about Eudoxus' model as he backs off and spends some time doing essentially philosophic reasoning about what has to be true of the celestial run." Duration: 10:39 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 7 - Evidence Problems: Real vs. Apparent Motion., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.7
    Synopsis: This video reviews Apollonius' Theorem. Opening line: "I'm only gonna go about five more minutes before I take a break, but I wanna look briefly at Apollonius' Theorem." Duration: 10:55 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 8 - The Almagest: a Summary of Books I-XIII., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.8
    Synopsis: This video introduces Ptolemy. Opening segment: "Has everybody who wants to be on trunk given me their information? All right, it'll be up here after class. Please do so, cuz I can put you on, but I can't do it if I don't know your email. All right, Ptolemy." Duration: 12:59 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 9 - The Ptolemaic Model: the Solar, Planetary, and Lunar Theories., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.9
    Synopsis: This video continues the discusion about Ptolemy and introduces the bisection of eccentricity. Opening line: "Now the overall system, this is a schematic, totally non to scale 100% not to scale. To begin with other than the moon Ptolemy had no idea how far any object was away." Duration: 13:16 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 10 - Ptolemy's Great Contribution: the Bisection of the Eccentricity., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.10
    Synopsis: This video continues the discusion about Ptolemy and reviews further the bisection of eccentricity, concluding that Ptolemy is twice violating Aristotle; the earth is not in the center and the motions are not uniform. Opening line: "All right let me go back now to Ptolemy and the bisection of the eccentricity." Duration: 7:38 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 11 - Reproducing the Retrograde Loops: Evidence for the Ptolemaic Model., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.11
    Synopsis: This video reviews Jim Evan's approach to the Hipparchian model and retrograde loops. Opening line: "Okay that's the background. I'm now gonna present Evans' approach to this." Duration: 7:47 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 12 - Calculating the Loops: Using Observations to Get the Orbital Elements., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.12
    Synopsis: This video discusses Noel Swerdlow's paper. Opening line: "Swerdlow, in an attempt to explain that, and it's in this paper, gives you a way as he says at the bottom here where I marked it out. Gives you a way of having the radius ratio." Duration: 5:48 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 13 - The Goals of Ptolemaic Astronomy: Qualitative, not Quantitative, Accuracy., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.13
    Synopsis: This video reviews Ptolemaic Astronomy. Opening line: "At any rate, though, it's very good science." Duration: 7:05 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 1 - Part 14 - The Implications of Ptolemaic Astronomy: Successes, Shortcomings, and the Essence of Good Science., 2014-09-02; gc.phil167.14
    Synopsis: This video reviews concludes the first lecture, with an assessment of Ptolemaic Astronomy. Opening line: "So what's the achievement of Ptolemaic astronomy and what are the shortcomings? Let's start with the achievement." Duration: 8:55 minutes. Segment: Class 1, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 1 - Turning Data into Evidence: Evidence and Hypotheses in Ptolemaic Astronomy., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.15
    Synopsis: Provides a definition of the term 'working hypothesis'; stresses that evidence is a relation between data and claims that reach beyond them; reviews three working hypothesis of celestial mechanics. Opening line: "All right, so let me start. I use the term working hypothesis very differently from its standard use." Duration: 16:02 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 2 - Islamic Astronomy: The Standard Story., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.16
    Synopsis: Places the publication of Copernicus' De Revolutionibus in light of the printing press; stresses that the printing press transformed higher learning; reviews how ancient learning came into western Europe via Islam; discusses the rise of the universities, textbooks, and a translation of the Almagest. Opening line: "All right. Now, I'm not going to put up a slide immediately because I don't have an appropriate slide to discuss with this right away." Duration: 7:01 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 3 - Islamic Astronomy: Ibn al-Shatir, and Innovative Astronomical Research in the Islamic World., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.17
    Synopsis: Tells how Edward S. Kennedy acquired a manuscript that turns out to be a comprehensive alternative to Ptolemaic astronomy by Ibn al-Shatir; emphasizes that Copernicus was indebted to Islamic science. Opening line: "In 1957, Edward S Kennedy, a professor at the American university in Beirut, Lebanon." Duration: 12:45 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 4 - Regiomontanus: Some Key Pre-Copernicus Publications in Astronomy., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.18
    Synopsis: Introduces Georg von Peuerbach and Regiomontanus (Johannes Mller von Knigsberg); discusses the project to print in the original Greek the whole of the Almagest, Euclid, Apollonius, and Archimedes. Opening line: "All right, so now I'm back to what happened in Europe after 1450." Duration: 7:22 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 5 - Copernicus: a Brief Biography., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.19
    Synopsis: A brief biography of Copernicus. Opening line: "So let me tell you a little about Copernicus now, 1473 to 1543, that means he lived 70 years." Duration: 6:39 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 6 - Copernicus' System: The Postulates, and Some Solutions to Classic Problems in Ptolemaic Astronomy., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.20
    Synopsis: A brief review of Copernicus' System. Opening line: "All right, with that as background, let's look at the commentary, all it's very clean." Duration: 11:24 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 7 - Heliocentrism: Copernicus' Mathematical Transform (of Ibn al-Shatir's Mathematical Transform) of Ptolemy's epicyclic system., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.21
    Synopsis: Reviews the process by which Copernicus arrived at Heliocentrism. Opening line: "How did he get to heliocentricity? Well here's a passage from Almagest." Duration: 8:38 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 8 - Copernicus' Place in the History of Astronomy: In What Senses Did Copernicus Inaugurate a Revolution?., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.22
    Synopsis: Reviews the challenge Copernicus posed to religious authority, and the dominant worldview. Opening line: "There were Copernican revolutions. The one revolution is a challenge to authority." Duration: 5:51 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 9 - The Structure of De Revolutionibus Orbium Coelestium: a Summary of What Copernicus Did., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.23
    Synopsis: An Overview of the De Revolutionibus. Opening line: "All right, so the next slide is from Tom Coon of course." Duration: 9:41 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 10 - Eliminating the Equant: the Method of Triangulations, and the Presupposition of Ptolemaic Theory., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.24
    Synopsis: Detailed explanation with an example on removing the equant. Opening line: "All right. How to get rid of the equant. I'm gonna be quick on this." Duration: 9:55 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 11 - A Possible Reason Why Copernicanism Was Accepted: Inference to the Best Explanation., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.25
    Synopsis: Although there is no empirical grounds whatsoever for preferring Copernican Astronomy to Ptolemaic Astronomy, Copernicanism was accepted. This video begins to propose an answer as to why. Opening line: "All right let me ask a question, and and I'm almost done with Copernicus but I want to pause for a moment and ask why should anybody at the time prefer Copernican astronomy to Ptolemaic astronomy." Duration: 8:21 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 12 - An Alternative Reason Why Copernicus's Theory Should Have Been Preferred to Ptolemy's: Bringing Empirical Evidence to Bear on Scientific Questions., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.26
    Synopsis: Although there is no empirical grounds whatsoever for preferring Copernican Astronomy to Ptolemaic Astronomy, Copernicanism was accepted. This video concludes with an answer as to why. Specifically, the system was seen as beautiful. Opening line: "I'm gonna give you a different reason for preferring Copernican astronomy, though." Duration: 5:16 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 13 - Tycho at Hven: the Collection of a Preciseand UniformBody of Observations., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.27
    Synopsis: A brief biography of Tycho Brahe at Hven; his removal from his post; transition to modern astronomy. Opening line: "All right, Tycho Brahe. This is a quote from the best biography we have of him." Duration: 11:13 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 14 - Theory, Empirically Driven: Tycho's Account of Solar Motion, His Attempts to Correct Observational Error, and His Search for Stellar Parallax., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.28
    Synopsis: A continued examination of Tycho Brahe at Hven and his data collection techniques; reviews the issues of parallax correction and atmospheric refraction correction. Opening line: "From 1578 to 1597, he did observations of the sun crossing the meridian altitudes." Duration: 10:01 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 2 - Part 15 - A Crisis in Mathematical Astronomy: the Calculational Equivalency of Three Different Systems, and the Attraction of Pyrrhonism., 2014-09-09; gc.phil167.29
    Synopsis: Synopsis: Points out that there is no way to choose between the 3 systems if the only form of empirical data we have are observed longitudes and latitudes; places astronomy in the historical context of the mid-16th century and reviews the rise of Pyrrhonism. Opening line: "At any rate, what I want to lead up to now, and I've got four minutes, I'll do my best with this. What we've got here in the 1590s is three systems." Duration: 7:01 minutes. Segment: Class 2, Part 15.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 1 - Astronomical Data in 1600: the Evidential Challenges in Empirical Astronomy., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.30
    Synopsis: Reviews the state of mathematical astronomy in 1600. Describes how Kepler gained access to Tycho Brahe's observations. Opening line: "A couple of remarks from last week. First Melissa, I think it was Melissa, that's I spoke to you as you walked in who made the remark about Tycho having a gold nose." Duration: 13:17 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 2 - Kepler: a Brief Biography, and the Appreciation of Physical Theory., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.31
    Synopsis: Gives a brief biography of Johannes Kepler. Provides the background in which Kepler did his work. Opening line: "So a little about Kepler. Kepler was born in 1571, he died in 1630, so he didn't quite make 60 years old." Duration: 13:48 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 3 - Towards Disentangling the Various Observed Motions: Astronomia Nova, Real Planetary Movement, and the First and Second Inequalities., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.32
    Synopsis: Introduces Kepler's arguments on how to analyze the motions of the planets. Gives some history on his book came to be published. Describes details about retrograde motion and the implications for describing orbits. Opening line: "In the introduction you'll be reading next week, this is Astronomia Nova." Duration: 6:29 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 4 - The Problems Kepler Faced: Imprecision in Observation, Interpolation, and the Observational Data Themselves., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.33
    Synopsis: Discusses Kepler's analysis of the sources of error in astronomical observations and predictions. Includes observational error, parallax, refraction, and optics. Discusses implications of errors in identifying discrepancies between theory and observation. Opening line: "The approach Kepler takes in Astronomia Nova is to start with various approaches, all three." Duration: 6:40 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 5 - Astronomia Nova: the Overall Structure., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.34
    Synopsis: Outlines the book Astronomia Nova. Describes the organization of the book as a flowchart of reasoning. Opening line: "At any rate, let's turn to the book itself. This is the title page in English, as translated by Bill Donahue." Duration: 7:32 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 6 - Astronomia Nova, Part 1: the Actual Sun, an Experimentum Crucis, and the Problem of Latitudes., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.35
    Synopsis: Describes Kepler's argument for basing orbital predictions on the actual position of the Sun instead of the hypothetical mean position. Opening line: "All right, let's go back to part one. I said what point in part one is to establish that we should be referring all motions to the actual Sun, not to the mean Sun." Duration: 9:22 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 7 - Astronomia Nova, Part 2: the Vicarious Hypothesis, and Mars' Heliocentric Longitudes., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.36
    Synopsis: Shows how Kepler analyzed the orbit of Mars. Follows Kepler's reasoning which removes the Ptolemaic concept of the equant. Opening line: "Part 2. He now decides to take a first shot at the Mars orbit." Duration: 10:52 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 8 - Astronomia Nova, Part 3: the Earth-Sun Orbitand Bisected Eccentricityin the Copernican/Tychonic Systems., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.37
    Synopsis: Discusses Kepler's analysis of the Earth's orbit. Concludes that the Earth's orbit is eccentric. Opening line: "Which gets me to part three. And I stay with this for a moment." Duration: 8:45 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 9 - Astronomia Nova, Part 3: Transferring the Argument to the Ptolemaic System., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.38
    Synopsis: Shows how Kepler's eccentric orbits are transferred into the Ptolemaic system. Opening line: "That's great if Mars is going around the sun. What about Ptolemy?" Duration: 9:58 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 10 - Astronomia Nova, Part 4: the Area Rule, the Oval, and the Ellipse., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.39
    Synopsis: Describes Kepler's new rule that the orbital velocity is inversely proportional to the distance from the Sun. Opening line: "Okay, here's where we've gotten to. We've gotten to where the Earth-Sun orbit has got bisected eccentricity, and therefore, Kepler can go ahead and say velocity in the Mars orbit is inversely proportional to the distance of Mars from the Sun." Duration: 8:40 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 11 - Astronomia Nova, Part 4: Using Triangulation to Show that Mars' Trajectory is An Oval., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.40
    Synopsis: Shows how Kepler proves the orbit of Mars is an oval. Opening line: "And then, he does now the typical Kepler thing to do. He starts looking at other ways of considering this whole manner." Duration: 6:22 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 12 - Astronomia Nova, Part 4: the Diametral Distance Rule, and Settling on the Ellipse., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.41
    Synopsis: Shows how Kepler derived the elliptical shape of orbits. Opening line: "Okay, then he notices something that really strikes him and I'll just read it. The breadth of the lunule of Chapter 46 above." Duration: 11:49 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 13 - Physical Theorizing: a Magnetic Account of Planetary Motion., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.42
    Synopsis: Discusses Kepler's magnetic theory of planetary orbits. Opening line: "He now asks what's the physics of this?" Duration: 7:10 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 3 - Part 14 - Accepting the Account: Evidential Arguments for Kepler's Innovations, and the Extent to Which Three Interrelated Principles Hold., 2014-09-16; gc.phil167.43
    Synopsis: Summarizes Kepler's innovations and the evidence supporting them. Opening line: "So, look, there are questions of evidence here. There are really five principles, and in the notes I go through all five." Duration: 13:12 minutes. Segment: Class 3, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 4 - Part 1 - Working Hypotheses: Kepler, and the 1911 Solvay Conference., 2014-09-23; gc.phil167.44